Friends of the Libraries; Records ua580.020
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Friends of the Libraries Records
1981-2006
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Friends of the Libraries of the University at Albany
ua580.020
5 cubic ft.
The Friends of the Libraries Records contain the day-to-day activities of this University at Albany organization comprised of faculty, staff, alumni, and community members.
Administrative History
In 1981, Anne Roberts, Assistant Director of Libraries at the University at Albany, brought together a group of faculty and staff interested in supporting the libraries and this group formally became the Friends of the Libraries the following year. The group welcomed alumni, community residents, current and retired faculty members, and anyone interested in the future of the University Libraries. The organization sponsored gifts and donations to the University Libraries. As part of its efforts, the Friends of the Libraries preserved Dewey Library's stained glass windows and murals in the downtown campus buildings. The Friends of the Libraries created the Alice Hastings Murphy Scholarship to provide for student library employees and full-time library staff members who want to become librarians and named it for the former Director of Libraries from 1956 to 1970. The Friends of the Libraries' annual book sale every fall funded student scholarships and awards.
The Friends of the Libraries also promoted community outreach. It held open talks called Wednesday Wanderings where professors and local, prominent figures spoke about Albanys history, their own research, and other interesting topics. The organization also went on historic outings in the Capital District, Historic Hudson Valley and beyond, including Olana, Hyde Park, Mohonk Mountain House, Lake George, and the Glimmerglass Opera. The group ended in 2006.
The Friends of the Libraries remained active until 2006. Presidents included: Alice Hastings Murphy (1982-1985, 1992-1999), Ruth Abele (1985-1986), Ben-Ami Lipetz (1986-1988, 2003-2006), Kenneth Doran (1988-1992), and Charles Ciaccio (1999-2003). The Library Liasons included Anne Roberts (1981-1986, 1988), Bonita Bryant (1986-1990), Dorothy Christiansen (1989-2002), Roberta Armstrong (2002-2006), and Geoff Williams (2006).
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the administrative records and community outreach efforts of the Friends of the Libraries. It has the organization's monthly meeting agendas and minutes as well as fliers for monthly talks, annual book sales, and materials about community outings. There are VHS tapes with recordings of talks held in conjunction with the University's celebration of its sesquicentennial.
The collection also contains two large scrapbooks that President Anne Roberts created. The scrapbooks document the Friends of the Libraries outreach events. These include the annual book sale as well as academic talks with prominent professors of the University, such as the History Departments Sung Bok Kim and the Atmospheric Science Departments Bernard Vonnegut. The scrapbooks also contain information on Friends of the Libraries outings, with photos of Olana and Sagamor as well as fliers and RSVP forms. The scrapbooks also include information about donations and library support.
Arrangement of the Collection
Arranged into 3 series. Series 1 and 2 are ordered alphabetically, while Series 3 maintains the original order of the final 2016 donation.
Acquisition Information
Anne Roberts, University Library Liason to the Friends of the Library, initially donated the scrapbooks in 1989. Former President Ben-Ami Lipetz donated the majority of remaining materials in 2006, with the exception of Series 3 which was transferred by Lorre Smith in 2016.
Related Materials
Related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives can be found in the subject guide for Criminal Justice and Prisons.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Travel; Library fund raising--United States; Library outreach programs--United States; Friends of the library--United States; Albany (N.Y.); Agendas (administrative records); Photographs; Correspondence; Files by subject; Minutes; Scrapbooks; Budgets; Fliers (printed matter); UAlbany Faculty & Alumni Papers; State University of New York at Albany. Friends of the Libraries; State University of New York at Albany. University Libraries; State University of New York at Albany
- Administrative Records, 1981-2006; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains agendas and minutes of the organization from 1981 to 2006. The organization for agendas and minutes is different from 2003 to 2006 because the material came to archives in its original order. In these files, there is supplemental material along with administrative records. There are also multiple agendas for some months because President Ben-Ami Lipetz took notes on his agenda copies (any of these will make note of it in the upper right hand corner).
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1981 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 1)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1982 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 2)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 3)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 4)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 5)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 6)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 7)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 8)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 9)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 10)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 11)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 12)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 13)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 14)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 15)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 16)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 17)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 18)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1999 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 19)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 20)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 21)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 22)
  - Agendas, Minutes and Supplemental Materials, 2003-2006 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 23-24)
  - Alice Murphy Scholarship, 1994; 1998; 2000; 2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 25)
  - Awards and Donations, 1982-2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 26)
  - Board Members, 1986-2006 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 27)
  - Book Bags, 1989-2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 28)
  - Book Marks-PR/Productions, 1993-1996 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 29)
  - "25 and Going Strong"-Booklet, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 30)
  - Budgets and Expenditures, 1983-2002 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 31)
  - Bylaws, 1983; 1987; 1988; 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 32)
  - Calendars, 1990-2002 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 33)
  - Campaign for the University Library, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 34)
  - Committee/Research Documents, 1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1981-2002 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 36)
  - Grants, Supporting Programs, 1983-1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 37)
  - History, 1969; 1977; 1980-1983; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 38)
  - Mailing Lists, 1987-2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 39)
  - Member card, 1985; 1988-1989; 1993-1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 40)
  - New Hampshire Primary Talk, Kathleen Kendall, 1996 February 22 (Cassette 1)
  - Newsletter, 1982 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 41)
  - Notes from ACRL Session, 1989 April 21 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 42)
  - Potential Recruits, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 43)
  - Scrapbooks, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 44)
  - Sesquicentennial Historical Essay Contest-"The Residence Halls and their Impact on Student Life"-Mary Ellen Nankes, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 45)
  - Sesquicentennial Historical Essay Contest-"A Monoloth from Humble Origins"-Matthew Fredrick, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 46)
  - Sesquicentennial Historical Essay Contest-"The James Allen JR. Collegiate Center: An Experiment in Undergraduate Education"-Thomas Pullyblank, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 47)
  - Sesquicentennial Historical Essay Award, 1991-1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 48)
  - Sesquicentennial Program 1 - Program is "History of the University at Albany," led by Professor Kendall Birr, Faculty, Emeritus, Department of History., 1994 February 24; Duplicate tape exists. Event also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 1)
  - Sesquicentennial Program 2 - Program is "New York State College for Teachers: The 1940s and and 1950s," led by Dr. Theodore Fossieck, Jacquelyn Mann Gavryck, Professor M.E. Grenander, Dr. Oscar E. Lanford, Professor Wallace Taylor, and Louise Hesnney Waterman., 1994 March 17; Duplicate tape exists. Event also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 2)
  - Sesquicentennial Program 3 - Program is "State University of New York at Albany: Years of Growth and Change, 1960s" led by Professor Arthur Collins, Professor Randolph Gardner, Stuart Horn, Professor Mauritz Johnson, Dr. Elmer Mathews, Alice Hastings Murphy, and Judy A. Mysliborski., 1994 April 28; Duplicate tape exists. Event also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 3)
  - Sesquicentennial Program 4 - Program is "Design and Construction of the Uptown Campus," led by Professor Raymond Bromley, Professor Edward Crowley, Professor Thomas H. Littlefield, Robert Ruckterstuhl, and Elwin Stevens., 1994 September 22; Duplicate tape exists. Event also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 4)
  - Sesquicentennial Program 5 - Program is "The University at Albany: Changing for the 1970s and 1980s," led by Professor Mark Berger, Frederick K. Brewington, Gloria DeSole, Dr. David W. Martin, Professor Joan Schulz, and Victoria Zeldin., 1994 October 15; Duplicate tape exists. Event also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 5)
  - Sesquicentennial Program 6 - Program is "Kate Stoneman, normal School Alumna and First Woman Lawyer in New York State," led by Geoffrey Williams, University Arvhivist and Campus Records Officer., 1994 November 17; Duplicate tape exists. Event also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 6)
  - Sesquicentennial Programs, 1-3, 1994 February-1994 April; Duplicate tape exists. Events also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 7)
  - Sesquicentennial Programs, 4-6, 1994 September-1994 November; Duplicate tape exists. Events also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 8)
  - Source Guide, 1994; 1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 49)
  - "Spinning Straw into Gold: A Look at Cuesta College's Friends of the Library", 1999 September (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 50)
  - Spring-Fall Letters, 1989-2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 51)
  - Student Achievement Award, 1992-2001 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 52)
  - Suggested Distribution List, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 53)
  - University at Albany Perspectives, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Records), Folder 54)
- Community Outreach, 1982-2003; 2
  This series has annual book sale promotions, brochures, outing fliers, outing photos, and left over exhibit pieces on the Friends of the Libraries. This series also has information on monthly talks that the Friends sponsored. These are called Community Conversations or Wednesday Wanderings. Speakers of these talks included prominent professors and members of the community.
  - Booksale, 1983-2002 (Box 2 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 1)
  - Brochures, 1989-1990; 1999 (Box 2 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 2)
  - Comment and Interest Summary Cards, 1982 (Box 2 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 3-4)
  - Community Conversations, 1982-1994 (Box 2 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 5-7)
  - Directions and Pamphlets, Undated (Box 2 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 8)
  - Exhibit, 1990; 1993; 1998 (Box 2 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 9)
  - Exhibit, 1994 (Box 3 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 1)
  - Exhibit, Undated (Box 3 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 2)
  - Glimmerglass Opera Outings, 1999-2003 (Box 3 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 3)
  - Library Hours, 1983 (Box 3 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 4)
  - Interactive Media Center-Information Sheet and Orientation, 1994 September (Box 3 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 5)
  - Outing Brochures, Undated (Box 3 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 6)
  - Outings, 1984-2002; 1981-2006 (Box 3 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Outings and Lectures, Undated (Box 3 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Outings-Taken by Jacqueline A. Gavryck-Includes Letter, Undated (Box 3 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 9)
  - Plaque, 1984 (Box 3 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 10)
  - Proclamation, Albany, New York-Mayor Jennings, 2006 May 12 (Flat-file 1)
  - Scrapbook 1, 1982-1983 (Oversized 1)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1984-1986 (Oversized 2)
  - Library Tour, 1997 (Box 3 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 11)
  - University at Albany Libraries-Updates and Progress, 1994; 1996-1998; 2001 (Box 3 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 12)
  - Volunteers, 1982 (Box 3 (2-Community Outreach), Folder 13)
- Administrative Binder, 2003-2006; 3; 0.17 cubic ft.
  original order and labels from binder.
  Binder that contained adminstrative records from 2003 until the group ended in 2006.
  - Mailer, ca. 2006 (Box 4 (3-Administrative Binder), Folder 1)
  - Board Members and list of friends, 2005-2006 (Box 4 (3-Administrative Binder), Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 2003 (Box 4 (3-Administrative Binder), Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 2004 (Box 4 (3-Administrative Binder), Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 2005 (Box 4 (3-Administrative Binder), Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 2006 (Box 4 (3-Administrative Binder), Folder 6)
  - By-Laws, 2004 (Box 4 (3-Administrative Binder), Folder 7)
  - Community Conversations/Outings, 2003-2005 (Box 4 (3-Administrative Binder), Folder 8)
  - Annual Book Sale, 2004-2005 (Box 4 (3-Administrative Binder), Folder 9)
  - Glimmerglass Outing, 2005-2006 (Box 4 (3-Administrative Binder), Folder 10)
  - Outings, 2005-2006 (Box 4 (3-Administrative Binder), Folder 11)